"Choosing the Safest and Most Effective Sunscreen"
(webinar recording)
Hello everyone and welcome.
I’m Dr. Michael Greger, coming to
you from my stationary treadmill.
I see your comment in the chat
there, Richard. No jogging.
I will not make people seasick.
This is a CME-approved webinar.
Continuing medical education for doctors
and other medical professionals as such.
I’m proud to declare I have no
relevant financial relationships
with ineligible companies to disclose.
That kind of declaration statement is
necessary, given the long, chequered
past of big pharma secretly propping
up paid shills to push their products.
Now they just not-so-secretly pay salespeople to
prop up their products—but I am not one of them.
If at any time you run into any technical
difficulty, there is live chatroom staff
standing by. Let me paste that link into
the chat for everyone. There you go.
If they’re unable to help, we have
the NutritionFacts.org staff standing
by too. Let me paste that into the chat as well.
Okay. Please reserve the Q&A button you see
in the Zoom window—oh, did I not stop sharing?
I’m sorry. I should have stopped
sharing my blank video. All good now.
Okay, where are we? Please reserve the Q&A
button in the Zoom chat window
there to ask content questions.
Today’s webinar is only an hour, but I’ve
reserved lots of time for Q&A at the end.
So please feel free to put your questions in
the Q&A at any time throughout the webinar,
and our NutritionFacts team will
compile them to be answered at the end.
You don’t have to worry about taking notes
or anything, as after the webinar is over,
we’re not only going to send
you a full recording of it,
but also a free link to download all
the videos in high resolution so you
can see the videos in their full-resolution glory.
Today we are going to be talking
about a subject that has gotten
surprisingly controversial—for both
preventing skin aging and skin cancer.
The pros and cons, the best way to apply
it, and—given the recent findings that
the absorption of sunscreen chemicals into the
bloodstream is greater than previously thought—
how to choose the safest brands.
All the videos I’m going to be
showing you are eventually going
to be up on NutritionFacts.org,
but you get to see them right here, right now.
And we start with the single most important thing,
with a video entitled: "The Single Most
Important Thing to Maintaining Youthful Skin."
Let's do this.
Considered the single most
important practice
for maintaining youthful skin:
the daily application
of sunscreen
and taking
other protective measures,
like wearing a hat.
All the other things
you can do for your skin
pale in comparison,
especially for those
with pale skin.
Up to 90 percent
of visible facial aging
among people
with lighter skin tones
is due to exposure to sunlight.
Those with darker skin
are relatively protected
due to their built-in
melanin sunscreen,
but they're still affected.
Sun damage in darker skin
tends to be less about wrinkles
and more
about pigmentation issues,
such as uneven skin tone,
dark patches,
and small dark bumps
on the face.
Either way,
dermatologists now agree
that there is
nothing more important
to slow the signs of aging
than to protect your skin
from the sun.
To illustrate, here's
a dramatic photo of a trucker
who spent decades
getting more sun
on the left side of his face
through
his driver's side window,
reminiscent of a Batman villain.
Factors like sun exposure
and smoking
can make us look
up to 11 years older.
Compare that to extensive
cosmetic surgery—
a face lift and a neck lift,
and removing excess skin
from both the upper
and lower eyelids,
and a forehead lift,
which combined,
can make us look
about eight years younger.
So, a healthy lifestyle
may work even better.
Protecting your skin
from the sun
should be a lifelong endeavor.
This can involve
applying sunscreen,
wearing sun-protective clothing,
hats, and sunglasses,
and avoiding direct sunlight
during the peak hours
of 10:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.
and instead
seeking shady, covered areas.
Sunbathing is frowned upon,
even with sunscreens
like zinc oxide
or titanium dioxide that offer
broad-spectrum protection
against both UVA
and UVB rays.
We now know
that other wavelengths,
such as near infrared,
that are not covered
by sunscreens
also contribute to skin aging.
Men and women
who use tanning beds
appear significantly older
than those who don't,
and white women who sunbathe
appear years older
than they actually are,
similar to what is seen
with smoking.
UVA rays are primarily
responsible for skin aging,
whereas UVB are the rays
that cause sunburn,
but a broad-spectrum sunscreen
covering both is recommended
since both types of UV
contribute to cancer risk.
To prevent skin cancer,
the American Academy
of Dermatology recommends
sunscreen with an SPF of 30
or higher,
but an SPF even as low as 15
can help prevent skin aging.
How do we know?
Because it's been
put to the test.
Despite the widespread belief
that the use of sunscreen
would prevent skin aging,
all we had was data
on hairless mice.
That is, until ten years ago.
Nine hundred adults
were randomized
either to years
of daily sunscreen use
or to continue with
their own discretionary use.
(It was considered unethical
to withhold protection
by giving people
placebo sunscreen.)
In the end, 77 percent
in the recommended
daily sunscreen group
were applying sunscreen
at least three to four days
per week
compared with only 33 percent
in the discretionary use group.
Would that be
enough of a difference
to make a difference?
Yes, there was
significantly less skin aging
in the instructed
daily use group.
In fact, they suffered
no detectable increase
in skin aging
over the four-and-a-half-year
study.
The researchers concluded
"Regular sunscreen use
retards skin aging in healthy,
middle-aged men and women."
Okay, so to reiterate, there's nothing
more important to slow the signs of
aging than to protect your skin from the sun.
This involves avoiding direct sunlight
since they're skin aging wavelengths
not covered by sunscreens and wearing
a daily SPF 30 plus sunscreen proven
to slow aging in a randomized controlled trial.
Okay, but what if you care less about how
you look and more about avoiding cancer.
Has sunscreen been similarly proven to prevent
skin cancer? Let's find out in my next video,
"Does sunscreen really prevent skin cancer?".
Let's find out.
Decades ago,
studies started bubbling up,
reporting that not only
was the use of sunscreen
not found to be protective
against skin cancer,
but it was associated with
significantly elevated risk.
But subsequent studies offered
the obvious explanation
of this paradox.
People who use sunscreen are
more likely to be sunbathers.
That's like finding those
who use motorcycle helmets
are more likely to die
on the highway.
It's not that sunscreen
and helmets aren't protective;
it's just
that they're associated
with engagement
in risky activities.
But you don't know,
until you put it to the test.
As I noted in my last video,
randomized controlled trials
have shown that regular use
of sunscreen
can arrest visible signs
of skin aging,
including
biopsy-proven reductions
in UV-related skin damage.
But are there
interventional trials
proving sunscreen
can prevent cancer?
Yes.
Organ transplant recipients
are highly susceptible
to skin cancers
because they have to be given
immune suppressants
to prevent organ rejection.
A group of 120 organ recipients
were equally informed
about sun protection measures,
but half were given free
broad spectrum
SPF 50+ sunscreen
for daily application
to their head, neck,
forearms, and hands.
After two years, there were
nine new basal carcinomas
in the control group
versus only two
in the sunscreen group.
That sounds good, but it may
have just been a fluke.
In contrast, there was
a highly significant difference
in the proportion of patients
who got new invasive
squamous cell carcinomas.
Eight new cases
in the control group
versus zero
in the sunscreen group.
But wait until you hear
about what happened
to their actinic keratoses,
the precancerous growths
that can turn into skin cancer.
They all started out
covered in them,
a total of 191 detected
in each group.
In the subsequent 24 months,
the control group
developed 82 new ones.
How many did
the sunscreen group develop?
Negative 102.
More than 100
precancerous growths
in the sunscreen group
spontaneously regressed
and vanished completely
(compared to 82 new growths
developing in the control group
without a single one
disappearing).
Their bodies, even in
their immunocompromised state,
could heal itself
once it just stopped
being bombarded with
so many cancer-causing rays.
Other randomized
controlled trials
have shown similar findings,
but generalizability
is limited.
The studies all used
high-risk populations,
for example, those living
in subtropical climates,
or with a personal history
of precancerous lesions.
So, cancer prevention efficacy
in the general population
would be expected to be less.
On the other hand, the studies
could also have underestimated
the impact since they were
relatively short-term
(not exceeding four years)
and, ethically, had to allow
the control group participants
to slather on
their own sunscreen,
which would dilute
the difference between groups.
For maximum effectiveness,
sunscreen needs to be
applied properly,
which apparently rarely happens
in the real world.
In a study of nearly 5,000
skiers and snowboarders,
almost no one,
only about 4 percent
were fully compliant
with sunscreen recommendations.
First, there's the amount.
The FDA standard
is two milligrams
per square centimeter.
What does that mean?
Use the teaspoon rule:
one teaspoon for your face,
head and neck,
one for the front
of your torso,
another for your back,
one teaspoon for each arm
and two teaspoons for each leg.
That's a total
of nine teaspoons.
That's about
the total volume equivalent
of a golf ball or shot glass,
to help you visualize it.
Unfortunately,
the average sunscreen user
may only apply a quarter
of the recommended amount.
This is why high SPF sunscreens
are often recommended,
like 50+ SPF.
Although the FDA recommends
a minimum SPF of only 15
to prevent skin cancer,
under normal
consumer conditions,
even an SPF of 50
may effectively give you
only an SPF of 12.5,
because most people
don't put on enough.
Randomized double-blind,
head-to-head,
split-face experiments,
where you're randomized
to apply one sunscreen
to one side of your face
and another sunscreen
to the other side,
show that in real life use,
SPF 100+ sunscreen works
significantly better
than SPF 50+ sunscreen.
More than 50 percent
of the participants
were sunburned more
on their SPF 50+ side
compared to only
about 5 percent
on their SPF 100+ side.
Now, a potential downside
of higher SPF sunscreens
is that they could provide
a false sense of security.
Those randomized
to an SPF 30 sunscreen
ended up spending
more cumulative time in the sun
than those receiving
an SPF 10 sunscreen,
as much as five times longer
in some cases.
What else?
Well, people tend to remember
to use sunscreen
on a sunny day at the beach,
but sun protection is needed
even on cloudy days,
since the UV rays
are not dampened
as much as visible light.
There's even a phenomenon
known as "cloud enhancement"
where overcast skies
can sometimes result
in even more UV reaching
the Earth's surface
compared to clear skies.
Sunscreen labels often suggest
waiting at least 15 minutes
after application
before going outdoors,
but when put to the test,
sunscreen was found
to start working immediately
with the full effect apparent
by minute ten.
However, if water resistance
is required,
it may be prudent to wait
the full 15 to 30 minutes
after application
before taking a dip.
The terms "waterproof"
or "sweatproof"
appear to be
meaningless marketing,
as no difference
in retention was noted
between "waterproof" products
and those that were
merely labeled
"water-resistant."
Both were better than
non-water-resistant products,
though,
which lost nearly
all their protective effects
within 20 minutes
of water immersion.
The suggestion that sunscreen
should be reapplied
every two to three hours
only applies under conditions
in which it is rinsed off
by water or sweat,
or rubbed off by friction
from clothing or sand.
Even after allowing sunscreen
to dry first for 20 minutes,
between 15 and 60 percent
of its protective effect
can be lost
after contact with sand.
Otherwise, if the recommended
amount is applied
and the sunscreen layer
is not disturbed,
SPF can be maintained
for as long as eight hours.
Oh, tons of content in that video.
I mean, I think the coolest thing was that
study showing the spontaneous regression of
more than a hundred precancerous
growths in the sunscreen group.
Vanishing completely, right?
Their bodies—even in that immunocompromised
state—could heal themselves when they just—
when we just—stopped bombarding them
with so many cancer-causing rays, right?
It reminds me of the famous Lifestyle
Heart Trial from Dean Ornish,
showing that you could, you know, open up
arteries without drugs, without surgery—
just by putting people on a
plant-based diet and lifestyle program.
Suggesting that their bodies
wanted to be healthy all along,
and all we had to do was remove the fork we
were stabbing ourselves with three times a day,
and then the body could just heal naturally
once we take away the kind of noxious stimuli.
And so, in this case, it’s
the UV rays from the sun.
Okay, so, you know—the teaspoon
rule, maybe go 50+ SPF.
And then sunny days, cloudy days—that cloud
enhancement thing I never heard of, that’s wild.
But okay, the one thing I didn’t
cover: which sunscreen is best.
And that’s what I’m going to be wrapping up with—
the best type of sunscreen to use.
What kind of sunscreen
should you use?
Cream-based is preferable
to spray-on,
since the completeness
of application
is more readily visualized.
To help with adequate coverage,
spray-on sunscreens should be
rubbed on immediately
after spraying.
Aerosolized sunscreens
are flammable
and can combust on skin
upon exposure to an open flame,
even after the sunscreen
has dried.
What's more,
the safety of breathing in
aerosolized sunscreen chemicals
has not been
adequately studied,
though frankly the same thing
could be said
about rubbing them
on your skin.
The concerns
surrounding sunscreen safety
are three-fold:
increased
intentional sun exposure,
vitamin D deficiency,
and untoward effects
from systemic absorption
of sunscreen chemicals.
In the 1800s, we first learned
that UVB caused sunburns
and formulated sunscreens
to block it.
Nearly a century later,
we learned
about the contribution of UVA.
Now, a full century later,
we are realizing that infrared
and visible light
may also be contributing
to cancer
and premature skin aging.
Sunlight comes to us
in three major bands:
visible light, ultraviolet,
and infrared.
Visible light includes
the colors of the rainbow—
red, orange, yellow, green,
blue, indigo, and violet,
or ROYGBIV.
Ultraviolet—UV—is to the right
of violet in ROYGBIV,
and infrared
to the left of red.
Sunscreen can protect us
against the free radical damage
of UV,
but half
of the free radical formation
in our skin from the sun
may be from the visible
or infrared spectrums,
which sunscreens
may not adequately cover.
So, that's where sun avoidance
strategies come in,
but you can imagine
how shade-seeking
could be undermined
by the solacement
of a sunscreen
security blanket.
What about vitamin D?
The theoretical concern
about sunscreen
affecting vitamin D status
does not seem to manifest
in the real world,
likely because
the UV dose necessary
for vitamin D production
is so low,
well before skin
turns a pinker shade.
However, concerns
about the systemic absorption
of sunscreen chemicals
were underscored
by the recent FDA bombshell
that not a single one
of sunscreen chemicals
in current use
can be considered
generally recognized as safe.
Only two active ingredients
got the green light,
the two non-chemical
"mineral" sunscreens:
titanium dioxide
and zinc oxide.
The revelation was based
on a growing body of evidence
that transdermal, meaning
through-the-skin, absorption
of sunscreen chemicals
was greater than
we previously thought,
raising unevaluated
safety concerns.
Unevaluated, because we
previously didn't think so much
got into our bloodstreams.
In 2019, a study published
in the Journal of
the American Medical Association
found that under maximum
usage conditions
over a period of days,
the blood levels
of all the sunscreen chemicals
they tested
exceeded the FDA threshold
that could potentially waive
further safety testing.
Then, in 2020, they found
that just a single application
of all the chemical sunscreens
they tested
surpassed the threshold.
Now, just because they're
absorbed into our system,
doesn't necessarily mean
they're unsafe.
It just means they need
to be tested for safety,
which, the FDA determined,
the multibillion-dollar
sunscreen industry
has so far failed to do.
The FDA concluded
that two ingredients
can be considered safe—
zinc oxide
and titanium dioxide,
and two can be
considered unsafe—
P.A.B.A.
and trolamine salicylate.
And the other 12 ingredients
that are currently marketed
have yet to be
sufficiently safety tested.
According to a review of more
than 700 sunscreen brands,
it appears P.A.B.A.
and trolamine
are no longer being marketed
in sunscreens
sold in the United States,
but they still may be available
in other countries.
Until the data are in
on the rest
of the chemical sunscreens,
I would recommend sticking
to the two mineral sunscreens.
Historically, they've tended
to be thicker and whiter,
which could lead
to even more severe underdosing,
but newer
micronized formulations
with smaller
mineral particle sizes
tend to be less noticeable.
This is particularly an issue
for those with darker skin.
The average built-in SPF
of black skin
(also known in the medical
literature as "ethnic skin"
or "SOC," skin of color)
is about 13 naturally,
compared with only about three
for white skin.
Though there haven't been
any interventional studies
on sunscreen effectiveness
for skin cancer prevention
in people with dark skin,
SPF 13 is not considered
sufficient sun protection;
so, the American Academy
of Dermatology recommends
regular sunscreen use
with an SPF of 30 or higher
for people of all skin types.
Unfortunately,
only about 12 percent
of non-Hispanic Blacks
and 31 percent of Hispanics
report regularly using
sunscreen,
compared to about 44 percent
of non-Hispanic whites.
Despite this,
the incidence of melanoma,
the deadliest skin cancer,
is five times lower
in Hispanics compared to whites
and more than 25 times lower
among Blacks.
However, the mortality rate
if you do get it
is higher among
African Americans,
presumed to be due
from delayed diagnosis.
Okay, so in short, only two sunscreen active
ingredients can be considered safe at this time,
and that’s the two so-called mineral
sunscreens: titanium dioxide and zinc oxide.
Though remember, in the first part of the video,
we talked about how that may really only cover UV—
the ultraviolet range—so sun
avoidance is still important,
since maybe half the free radicals created by
sun exposure are from the non-covered spectrum.
And so, so it’s—so avoidance, in addition to
using good sunscreens, is still important.
Absolutely outrageous that the safety
testing wasn’t done by industry,
but now they’re going to be
forced to—and it’s about time.
All right, Q&A time.
Happy to talk about anything that came up today
or any related topics on skin aging in general.
Got a whole chapter on it in How Not to Age,
and so we could bring up the pre-release sneak
preview and go through anything you’d like.
Let me just give NutritionFacts staff
five minutes to compile the questions
that have been submitted so
far through the Q&A button.
It’s not too late if you want to ask one now—
and then I will be right back.
[Q&A portion not captioned]